okay so you left San Francisco and you
returned to Oak Ridge and once again you
started your own studio is that correct
yes
um this was a
Oak Ridge uh during the war time Oak
Ridge was a fit City and and you had to
have a pass to get into it and there
were guard gates in all four corners of
the city
and one of these was called elza gate
um this was out at the East end of Oak
Ridge and there was a little Community
there that
um called Elsa
and we found a uh my brother and I found
a little low rent uh sort of uh I
believe that one time it had been a
motorcycle shop had a concrete floor it
was a concrete block building
and I said well this would be a great
place to start a holography studio
because it's away from traffic and it's
on a concrete floor and we can live here
you know there was Tennessee there's not
a lot of regulations about where you can
live and whatever so a lot of freedom
here
still to this day
yeah it's
it's less so
so it's a very free environment where I
live I I was just in Knoxville two years
ago almost to the day
yeah okay
um well
um this this was the low rent
section about grid so I named this
studio Baltic after the property on the
Monopoly
Monopoly equivalent
low rent property I've had a few times
playing Monopoly where uh Baltic
actually saved my rear end
and long about that time I met a couple
of guys I met Ed waske
and Phil Krieger who were both uh both
designers in like industrial designers
exhibit designers and showed them some
Holograms and they got disvascinated and
and we started turning away with
different ideas and things that we could
do and we decided that we would about
this time of the multiplex Holograms
were coming online when I saw that first
kiss hologram with Pam Brazier I had yet
another uh visual orgasm I just was I I
mean my whole body went rigid and
I can't describe the feeling I got from
seeing that and I showed I think I had
a bet and I showed that to them and it
had the exact same reaction with them we
were just spitting with the whole idea
so
at that time there was a museum there
still is a museum here in Oak Ridge
about the atomic energy program and we
we decided we'd present these Holograms
to the museum and suggest and exist
and they were equally cement with them
and so we worked for some time
unfortunately the whole deal fell
through largely because the multiplex
company was unable to
to take
their they had no distribution abusion
program no Channel program for uh for
selling Holograms and it was just sort
of a free
kind of thing and so the the deal for us
fell apart but we were able to uh able
to show a lot of holograms around and
got the community kind of excited about
that
and and it was gratifying to me because
that initial
demonstration that I'd seen way back in
1963 some of those same folks came to
programs at Baltic in in
1975 or 76 so it kind of came full
circle yeah and that was gratifying
but also at that time uh I had been
working for a company that was involved
in medical imaging using uh radio
nuclides
and this is a this is a technique that's
used even today to
the Physicians visualize
problems in your body by by giving what
they do is they give you a a radioactive
isotope of a chemical that that your
body normally would uptake anyway first
iodine is taking up by your thyroid and
they can give you a radioisotope of
iodine and your thyroid will take that
up and then they can form an image of
of that based on the gamma rays that are
emitted by the Radioactive
so I I had gotten fairly familiar with
the with the physical principles of all
this I'm certainly not a scientist or
anything but but I had a good
understanding of what was going on there
and you know it was just a short step to
say well gosh we could we could combine
holography
with this radioisotope
and then the physician instead of seeing
having to look at flat uh
there's a film could see
usual 3D visualization of say your
thyroid or or perhaps you had some kind
of a brain tumor problem or something
that that you could actually see it
what exactly provided the exposure
assuming there was an exposure onto like
a silver halide material or something
well uh the way the way this works is
that um
at that time in this
and this was just before CAT scans and
pet scans came online
they used what was called an anger
Central
hammer and this camera had a great big
Crystal of what amounts to Salt it was
sodium iodide
well sodium iodide is sensitive to gamma
radiation
if if a gamma ray strikes a sodium
iodide crystal that's been properly
treated it gives off a photon
and so essentially what you're doing is
you're transforming
to a visible visible Photon and you can
capture that on a on an oscilloscope
display screen yeah so what I did was I
I went down and talked to the local
hospital and the ideologist down there
and talk to the talk to some other folks
that had a had a uh what they call a
phantom head or a Alderson
called that
this cup of a
can feel with radioisotope
and I I went around in in this is
something that I've done all my life
that sort of skunk work steps
beg borrowed and assembled all this
equipment and I set up an airflex camera
on the oscilloscope so I manually
rotated this Phantom in front of the
anger camera and then recorded each
image off the oscilloscope with the
airflings and so I wound up with a 100
200 feet of film which I've been sent I
think it was double x
who Gary Adams at the multiplex company
and we created a hologram
[Music]
and uh and it actually worked very well
uh you could you could see the head
three dimensions dimensions and it had
two fake tumors in it and you could see
the the two fake tumors in three
dimensions
and uh so this was shown at the uh
Society of nuclear medicine I think in
1976 and also shown that the
International Center for photography
uh either in 76 or 77. yeah that was a
big show in New York right it was and
that was just that show was just
unbelievable that that was another
Epiphany yeah some someone actually
I I think it would be fair to say that
that was a big kickoff for holography
that show it was it was
you know from
from Jackson for uh putting up with this
hillbilly from uh Oak Ridge Tennessee in
all of my
bitching and whining and complaining and
all that but she got me into that show
and then the show later on the the same
holder games went to uh Sweden and
Victor Europe
but uh when I got up there in the show I
was just I mean it was it was astounding
what I saw and you know Lloyd was up
there Steve Benton was up there just a
lot of the uh a lot of the big names and
holography at that time attended and
exhibited
and one thing uh I hope you don't mind
me just rambling on you but go ahead one
thing that I saw at that time was um
Steve Benton's reflection hologram of
the train oh engine number nine exactly
and once again I I just had that moment
of epiphany I just stood stood in front
of that thing for for 15 minutes I could
not believe what I was seeing I had
never seen
uh you know I've made reflection whole
grains but I've never seen one like that
and I could I couldn't understand what
he was doing that was so different than
what I or any of the other folks that
were doing reflection Holograms why he
was getting such a high
it was so bright and so clear and so
Noise free just unbelievable
and uh so I I went and introduced myself
to him and talked to him at length and
and he explained this whole process
um which just fascinated me
the idea that
instead of of
King out the unexposed silver that you
actually
via a solvent type developer you
dissolve it and it precipitates back
onto the exposed silver so in effect
you're amplifying the whole image well I
that I went off on a on a five-year Trek
of of making my own emotions of making
my own developers and experimenting with
the developer that he and he had given
me it was just a whole episode
yeah some of those early uh some of
those early chemical formulas weren't
very good I remember working with the
mercuric chloride bleach
parabenzoquinone pbq those things were
awful bromine yeah oh I had I had all
that I had a big jar of bromine
at my house and I had to I finally had
to put it in the backyard I dug a hole
and put it in the back yard and that's
where I kept it it was that stuff was
awful yeah yeah I remember I worked with
all those things in the early days too
um and in fact you know the uh the
Mercury chloride is actually called
moncoven's intensifier and that was uh
actually uh Gabrielle lippman uh was
originally used that so that that has
that goes back to 1895 you know for in
terms of Litman type Imaging your
medical hologram was on display at the
Museum of Photography in Chicago for a
number of years wasn't it yeah it was
and uh and it disappeared
um I had uh I had a trip business trip
in 2000 and I stopped by and visited
Lauren buildings up there and asked her
I Leonard tour you know many years
before and asked her what had become of
it because I'd like to get it back and
uh she said that she didn't know what
had happened to it and uh so it's
I have a feeling that's out there or
something it's around yeah it's
somewhere it may be right appreciate it
if any of your listeners know where it
is that they could uh steer me back to
it it may be somewhere right in the
museum they'll find it yeah
have the original footage and I also
have some some duplicate whole dreams of
it so I'm not completely without it but
I would like to get the original bag you
went to Chicago for another company
right after uh Baltic didn't you
uh that was uh holographic Arts company
that uh that was a beautiful facility I
saw a picture of that on your website
that was beautiful oh it was fantastic
it was uh lee Lacy and uh in a group of
investors that were associated with the
Chicago Mercantile Exchange but Lee
Lacey uh
really the guy that kind of pushed the
whole idea
this is just a brilliant guy he he knew
uh right from the moment that he saw he
saw his First multiplex hologram he knew
that this could be applied commercially
and it uh that what needed to be done
was to set up a facility that could
Masters and then replicate them in a
volume
and he had a great visit and and he had
a lot of experience in the photography
commercial photography world so he knew
where to go to
the necessary equipment
and of course he worked with uh he
contracted with Lloyd and Dave Smith I
believe was involved in that and Mike
Khan was involved did they produce
Holograms at that facility or was that
just uh did they just form them out
um now we produced them there we had a
fabulous setup
we had what what I'm calling the and you
can see this on my website was uh the
Mark I believe it was the Mark II or the
Mark III Multiplex camera that
incorporated
of Lloyd's improvements to the original
Multiplex camera and the thing was of
course in typical Lloyd fashion was
built out of uh particle board which is
ideal for holography because it's
completely dead you know you know it's
massive and it's dead doesn't transmit
vibration very well and
um
uh we also had uh lee uh contracted with
Dave Smith to make the copying equipment
so we have the ability to uh to to run
off uh duplicates from the master
hologram uh and it was a very nice setup
that David created
then he also contracted with the
creonite corporation which builds
photographic processors and built a
custom uh processor that
that is a 24 inch wide they actually was
wider than that it would two
scripts simultaneously a 10 inch
holographic you know and automatically
process profit and it would
automatically replenish itself so that
uh you know it kept maintained its
chemicals together yeah
and he he bought a
for Mass we had we had a turntable that
I had built a little turntable and we
could he he of course had motion picture
equipment so we could we could shoot it
we
put the original Master on the multiplex
camera and then we could run off
thousands of copies well what what
chemistry were they running on that uh
self-replenishing processor automated
processor
d19 and uh and and stop math and Rapid
fixer
fixer it was just you know you're very
simple process and then it went through
a bleach with
we were using uh
for that was potassium ferrocyanide and
then it was uh you know of course that
had problems because it was a little bit
on the light sensitive side
that's what we used I believe taste them
up potassium ferrocyanide pleats for
transmission Holograms uh yeah well
that's I believe that's what we were
using there uh no I picked that back um
I mean we used an I uh an iodine base
bleach oh really yeah and that had a
they had had the advantage of uh it was
a lot more light stable and and actually
I believe it produced a more efficient
whole grams
okay at that time but now of course it's
been a long time so my memory is a
little bit weak on that but but I
believe we were using an iodine
and that of course of course has
problems with the
the processor uh in that we needed to
have uh special tanks and rollers that
could withstand that iodine bleach okay
for the Masters though
if we were using the fast repair sign on
so then you wound up back in Knoxville
right I've worked there for a year and
we got it all set up and everything was
running fine and I left uh left Chicago
which is
a uh to your list or Chicago is just
a wonderful City I mean it has
tremendous architecture
museums and food and just Transportation
the place is just a wonderful place and
I came back to Knox
and
um just kind of I have to say I dabbled
in holography for the next you know
eight or ten years and played around
with
Mount emotions and making various
apparatus and one thing in particular I
I want to recount is that I noticed on
your website you have a wonderful little
uh
sitting on making uh stereogram
portraits yeah and uh I I
looked through the whole thing and I
enjoyed what you what you came up with
there I had this idea that I ran across
some lenticular lenses and I decided
Well what what I need to do is make a
camera that has uh you know a couple of
dozen lenses arranged
so good I can
I can one a one exposure and capture
like two dozen images
taken from uh you know displaced
for about a foot
and then convert that into a hologram so
that I should
accomplished what you do with the
multiplex hologram in one shot
I actually built the camera and took
some exposures and and then it just it
became ever more complex to build the
rig that would uh would transfer that to
a reflection holder
it happened so I kind of uh that
languished in my garage for years and
finally I just tore the whole thing down
but I I still have that camera which I'm
kind of proud of that it actually works
wow
but but that's an idea that that any of
your listeners could do you just find
yourself an array of inexpensive lenses
and build yourself a little simple
camera you could you could do this you
could make a pinhole camera that
multiple pinholes stretched across for a
foot or two feet and put a piece of film
back in there and you'll have to build
some little baffles in there to separate
the images yeah but
and why you can you can dance and use
that to generate a master and create a
multiplex hologram that's not something
yeah yeah so you know and I also I want
to give your listeners I really I'm
rambling on here but I want to give your
listeners another little thing was uh I
did a lot of experiments based based on
what Steve Benton had scared me toward
with this uh what he called
intra-emulsive
should transfer and basically it's a
solvent type developer well I came up
with a formula which I believe would
probably even work with those the new
plates that are out there which
uh it's make one leader it would be five
grams of Elon and then 50 grams of
sodium sulfide one gram of potassium
bromide
30 grams of sodium metaborate which
serves as the buffer and then uh roughly
uh a tenth of a gram of sodium
thiocyanate which is
and then add water to uh make one liter
and this would make a very simple uh
gentle acting solvent developer which I
think would
well with the plates that are even out
there today and what what bleach would
you match that with
well at that time I was kind of taken
with that uh Cooper well was it Cooper
bromine
[Music]
um it was one of those bleach bleaches
like that uh that was floating around
out there that that worked pretty well
um and then of course there was Steve's
developer which also used the
thiocyanate for the solvent
he added in ascorbic acid which uh which
not only is a developer but also is a
solvent type developer and it's a little
sideline I tried this out hot what to
the drugstore and bought some vitamin C
and then I went to the grocery store
red devil lie
and mix the two together in proportions
and it actually worked worked out pretty
well as a developer no kidding yeah it
uh
you know you got to be careful with that
live but it has the property of getting
the pH way up and the ascorbic acid
served as a uh as a developing agent it
probably would work better
I had a buffer in it like like the
sodium metaborate but by itself it
seemed to work okay it's not something
there's some tips I
so tell us what you're doing now as as
we get ready to close out we're coming
up on 25 minutes again okay well I'm I'm
uh I have a wide range interest I draw
paint I'm a photographer and I'm also
involved heavily with the high Pig score
and then we make uh the 360 degree
immersive Imaging that you've seen a lot
of that in the real estate business for
home tours that where you
were usually around the whole room yeah
but we've also applied this now to
Homeland Security for video purposes oh
I see yeah 360 degree video and uh and
I've been involved with these folks for
about five years now and and it's just a
terrific experience uh
um I I continue with my long term
interest in the Imaging and after
visiting your site Frank I can't help
but say that I got
Five Points to get to making Holograms
again because it's just terrific what
you have up there well thank you very
much once you're inoculated with
holography I don't think it ever comes
out of the bloodstream I don't think it
is
well John
I want to thank you very much for taking
the time I know this was a long
interview but I think it was worth every
second that the clock ticked by having
you on the show and I I very much
appreciate you coming on and taking the
time and I'm sure
do as well well I appreciate it to you
and I like to say hello to all your
listeners
inviting me on the show and and I think
your Holo World side is just a great
service to the holographic community
hard work that uh you put into it again
and I'd encourage folks to get up there
and listen to some of these interviews
because they're as fresh today as when
they were originally recorded just
terrific steps though
oh thank you thank you so much John all
right have a great night bye
thank you